Guide to the J. H. Chappell Collection, 1922-1927, 1967 UA.30.01.0046
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. H. Chappell collection
1922-1927, 1967
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Chappell, John Herbert
UA.30.01.0046
4.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes; one pamphlet binder
J. H. Chappell graduated from Duke University in 1926 and was a college athlete. The collection includes Trinity College and Duke University memorabilia, student notebooks, correspondence, photographs and corresponding nitrate negatives, and other materials collected by Chappell during his years at Trinity College during its transition to Duke University. The memorabilia and ephemera include class grade reports, athletics events fliers, pins, banners and pennants, and Durham-specific advertising.
Access Restrictions
Negatives are closed to use. Corresponding prints are available in the collection.
Provenance
The J. H. Chappell Collection was received by the University Archives as a gift in 2002.
Biographical Note
John Herbert Chappell, of Durham, N.C., graduated from Duke University in 1926. He was a student during the University's transition from Trinity College. While at Duke, Chappell participated in both freshman and varsity football and baseball (lettering in baseball) and class wrestling. He was also a member of the "D" Club (for lettered athletes) and the Order of the Tombs.
Collection Overview
J.H. Chappell's papers relate to his time as a student at Trinity College and Duke University in Durham, North Carolina, 1922-1927, and include student notebooks, letters, photographs, and memorabilia, and other materials. One box includes a few Trinity College banners and pennants as well as pennants believed to be associated with Trinity Park High School. Of particular note is a pennant for the Hesperian Literary Society. Also included are Chappell's letters earned in athletics.
Ephemeral items include Chappell's admission card, class schedule cards for his four years, his membership certificate for the Order of the Tombs, grade reports, event fliers and programs, athletics memorabilia including ticket booklets and schedules, and Durham-specific business cards and advertisements.
There are photographs and negatives of Trinity/Duke athletes (football, baseball and track) as well as students playing in the snow on what is now East Campus. There is a 1925 panoramic photograph of the Duke University student body and faculty as well as of company c. 13th engineers at Fort Humphreys, Virginia (1927) in addition to a mounted photograph of a baseball team. The players are not in uniform but a few are wearing caps with a "D" on them. The negatives, most of them nitrate cellulose film, are closed to use; corresponding prints are in the collection.
Related Material
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) Reference Collection
Duke University Archives
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) Athletic Association Records
Duke University Archives
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) Baseball Scorebook
Duke University Archives
College sports -- North Carolina -- Durham; College students -- North Carolina -- Durham; College athletes -- North Carolina -- Durham; Memorabilia; Black-and-white photographs; Negatives (photographs); Cellulose nitrate film; Duke University -- Students; Duke University -- Alumni and alumnae; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Alumni and alumnae; Duke University -- Sports; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Baseball -- History -- 20th century; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Sports; Chappell, John Herbert; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Students; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Hesperian Literary Society
- Correspondence, 1922, 1923, 1928 (Box 1)
- Student Notebooks: Math and English, circa 1922-1926 (Box 1)
- Outlines of English Literature, 2 by Frank C. Brown and other members of the English Dept., 1925 (Box 1)
- Field Book, 1924 (Box 1)
- Class Schedule Cards, 1922-1926 (Box 1)
- Physics Laboratory Manual by C. C. Hatley, 1925 (Box 1)
- Booklet: Trinity College, 1923 (Box 1)
- Business and Advertisement Cards (Durham, N.C.), circa 1922-1926 (Box 1)
- Duke Athletics (ticket booklets, schedules), 1924-1927 (Box 1)
- Event Fliers and Programs, circa 1924-1927 (Box 1)
- French Examination Questions, 1923 Jan. 29 (Box 1)
- Trinity College Receipts, 1922-1926 (Box 1)
- Grade Reports and Admission Card, 1922, 1923 (Box 1)
- Certificate of Membership: Order of the Tombs, 1925 (Box 1)
- Duke Decals, undated (Box 1)
- YMCA and YWCA Handbook, 1922-1923; Constitution of the Men's Association of Trinity College, 1922 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous: Clippings, Signature Cards, 1924, undated (Box 1)
- Duke General Scholarship Fund: Certificate, 1967 (Box 1)
- Photographs, circa 1922-1926 (Box 1)
  Separated Materials
  Nitrate negatives have been removed from the photographs series and rehoused for preservation purposes. They are closed to use; corresponding prints are available.
- Negatives (NITRATE), 11 items One binder (Folder 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Negatives are closed to use. Corresponding prints are available in the photographs folder.
- Football Pin Beat Wake Forest, 1922 (Box 1)
- Trinity Banners and Pennants, circa 1922-1926 (Box 2)
- "D" letters, circa 1925-1926 (Box 2)
- Hesperian Literary Society pennant, circa 1922 (Box 2)